Morton N. Katz Papers VHP2006/31
CCSU Veterans History Project
Morton N. Katz Papers
Bulk, 1942-1946
1942 - 1946, 2006
VHP2006/31
CCSU Veterans History Project
137.0 Digital objects 1 interview DVD
This collection details experience of Morton N. Katz as he served in The U.S. Army, Airborne Division, during World War II. The collection contains army correspondence, regimental history, memoir, photographs, and oral history interview.
Katz, Morton N., (Morton Norris), 1919 -
Biographical/Historical note
Morton N. Katz was commissioned into the U.S. Army through the reserves program in 1940. After the attack on Pearl Harbor, he was ordered to attend training in Fort Benning, Ga. He completed infantry training and then went on for an additional six weeks of training with the parachute infantry. From there he was sent to England with the 503rd parachute infantry as a replacement battalion. Katz's unit prepared for the invasion of North Africa; however, they ended up arriving in Iran by train. His battalion then went to Italy, and by October of 1943 they were involved in combat near Naples. His unit was attached to the 82nd airborne division, and they went on to be part of the Anzio invasion and the Battle of the Bulge. When the Germans finally surrendered, the 82nd airborne division liberated Wobbelin concentration camp, which was a starvation camp outside of Ludwigslust, Germany. Katz was sent home in early 1946, but he remained in the reserves. He went on to use the G.I. Bill to attend law school, but he still took assignments with the reserves between semesters. After graduation from law school he accepted a position with the Civil Affairs Unit, where he stayed for 17 years. He was promoted to Colonel and served at the Pentagon. Katz kept in close touch with many from his unit, attending reunions of the 82nd Airborne Division Association.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for Research
Custodial History note
All manuscripts and photographs donated were digitized and digitally preserved. The donor retained all original manuscripts and photographs.
Online Access
An online exhibition of this veteran's papers can be accessed at project's website
United States. Army. Airborne Division, 82nd.; United States. Army. Parachute Infantry Regiment, 503rd.; Africa, North; Algiers (Algeria); Ardennes, Battle of the, 1944-1945; Fort Benning (Ga.); France; Germany; Iran; Italy; Wobbelin (Concentration Camp); World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, American
- Series I: Personal Papers, VHP2006/31.I
  - History of the 509th Parachute Infantry Battalion by Morton N. Katz, n.d.; VHP2006/31.I.1
  - Letter of appreciation to the 509th veterans of WWII at the 1973 reunion, April 1973; VHP2006/31.I.2
  - Letter and from about becoming a “distinguished member of the regiment” of the 502nd infantry regiment., Jan. 18, 1986; VHP2006/31.I.3
  - Letter about joining the newly formed Northeast Chapter of the 509th Parachute Infantry Association, September 1998; VHP2006/31.I.4
  - Interview synopsis, Nov 15, 2006; VHP2006/31.I.5
  - A Personal memoir of Morton N. Katz, December 2006; VHP2006/31.I.6
- Series II: Military Documents, VHP2006/31.II
  - Letter from Airborne Troops Commander about honorary members of the British Airborne Forces, Jun. 6, 1943; 2006/31.II.1
  - Letter from Henri Giraud, the general of French Army about wearing insignia as an honour to 503rd Parachute Regiment., Feb. 6, 1944; 2006/31.II.2
  - Letter of Farewell from LTG Mark W. Clark, Jul. 3, 1944; 2006/31.II.3
  - Award of the Purple Heart letter, Jul. 12, 1944; 2006/31.II.4
  - List of Purple Heart awardees, Feb. 11, 1945; 2006/31.II.5; 3.0 pages
  - Citation for bronze star medal for Morton Katz, 1944; 2006/31.II.6
  - 509th Parachute Infantry Battalion list of announced combat infantrymen, Apr. 20 1944; 2006/31.II.7
  - Unit citation for the 509th Parachute Infantry Battalion’s outstanding performance, Jun. 5, 1944; 2006/31.II.8
  - Farewell letter from major general Robert T. Frederick, Nov. 22, 1944; 2006/31.II.9
  - List of soldiers who receive various awards of medals, Jan. 5, 1945; 2006/31.II.10
  - Unit citation for the 509th Parachute Infantry battalion’s outstanding performance of duty, Mar. 20, 1945; 2006/31.II.11
- Series III: Publications, VHP2006/31.III
  - Drawing by Sora E. Rundell, one of the men who designed the Fifth Army soldier insignia, December 1943; 2006/31.III.1
  - Unpublished analysis of Disbandment of the 509th Parachute Infantry Battalion, 2006/31.III.2
  - Chronicle of 509th Parachute Infantry Regiment in WWII, n.d.; 2006/31.III.3
  - 509 Victory Song, 2000; 2006/31.III.4
  - Paraglide, an official publication of 82nd Airborne Division ASSN. INC., Fall 1964; 2006/31.III.5
  - News clipping from "Fayetteville (N.C.) Chapter News", Summer 1973; 2006/31.III.6
  - 502nd Regimental Newsletter, March 2000; 2006/31.III.7
  - First from Above: THE 509th Parachute Infantry Battalion in WWII by Paul V. DeGaeta, 2002; 2006/31.III.8; 124.0 pages
  - 82nd Airborne Division: America's Guard of Honor, 2004; 2006/31.III.9; 153.0 pages
  - Map of actual parachute assault into the Avellino (Frazier), n.d.; 2006/31.III.10; 153.0
  - History of 509th Parachute Infantry Battalion by Morton Katz, n.d.; 2006/31.III.11; 153.0
  - A Soldier's Saga: poem by Nicholas DeGaeta, n.d.; 2006/31.III.12
  - Excerpt from INFANTRY Part I: Regular Army book, about 509th Infanrty history, published by Center of Military History, US Army., n.d.; 2006/31.III.13
  - The Avellino Jump. from "U.S. Army in WWII, Mediterranean Theater of Operations, Salerno to Cassino"; by Martin Hlumenson., n.d.; 2006/31.III.14
  - "How American Paratroopers Took the Island of Ventotene" from "Once There Was a War" by John Steinbeck, 2006/31.III.15
- Series IV: Multi-Media, VHP2006/31.IV
  - Subseries A: Still Images, VHP2006/31.IV
    - Lt. Morton N. Katz, April 1942; VHP2006/31.IV.1
    - Lt. Morton N. Katz; 509th Parachute Infantry Battalion, 1942; VHP2006/31.IV.2
    - Master Rigger, Tech. Sgt. L.C. McLaney packs a parachute for Staff Sgt. C.E. Cole at the 503rd Parachute training post. Hungerford, England., August 1942; VHP2006/31.IV.3
    - T/5 Joseph R. Rambio and T/5 William Ates, members of the 503rd Parachute Battalion, fold their parachutes during training. Hungerford, England., August 1942; VHP2006/31.IV.4
    - Parachute riggers of the 2nd Battalion, 503rd Parachute Infantry, pack parachutes under the direction of master riggers in training. Chilton Foliat, Hungerford, Berkshire, England., August 1942; VHP2006/31.IV.5
    - T/5 H.G. Peace (of Laurel, Miss.) and T/5 C.C. Proctor (of Wichita, KA) pile up their packed parachutes at training quarters of the 503rd Parachute Battalion., August 1942; VHP2006/31.IV.6
    - Paratroopers of Headquarters Company, 503rd Parachute Battalion, getting ready to take off for the operation., August 1942; VHP2006/31.IV.7
    - Paratroopers of the 503rd Parachute Battalion going through a “mock up” dummy fuselage on the morning before a mass jump. Hungerford, England., August 1942; VHP2006/31.IV.8
    - Paratroopers of the assault platoon of the 503rd Parachute Battalion wait for the command to board the plane., August 1942; VHP2006/31.IV.9
    - Maj. D.R. Yardley (of Dublin, TX), Executive Officer of the 503rd Parachute Battalion., August 1942; VHP2006/31.IV.10
    - The parachutes open as men of the 2nd Battalion, 503rd Parachute Infantry, bail out from their C-47 planes. Berkshire, England., August 1942; VHP2006/31.IV.11
    - Paratrooper of the 503rd Parachute Battalion landed after a practice jump., August 1942; VHP2006/31.IV.12
    - Landing of the U.S. paratroopers while on cooperative maneuvers with the British troops - England., Sep. 19, 1942; VHP2006/31.IV.13
    - U.S. paratroopers receiving parachutes before a jump - England., Sep. 19, 1942; VHP2006/31.IV.14
    - Lieutenant Edmund J. Tomasik (of New Bedford, MA), 2nd Battalion, 503rd Parachute Infantry, checks equipment of his planeload during maneuvers. Hungerford, Berkshire, England., Oct. 2, 1942; VHP2006/31.IV.15
    - Lieutenant Edmund J. Tamasik (Left) and his planeload of paratroopers of the 2nd Battalion, 503rd Parachute Infantry. Hungerford, Berkshire, England., Oct. 2, 1942; VHP2006/31.IV.16
    - Colonel Monroe Wells (of Hartford, AL) mends a parachute in preparation of a jump - England, 1942; VHP2006/31.IV.17
    - U.S. paratrooper, PFC John Patton, mending a strap before making a jump with his battalion - England., Sep. 19, 1942; VHP2006/31.IV.18
    - Paratroopers of the U.S. Army, 2nd Battalion, 503rd Parachute Infantry, test their parachutes before a practice leap. Chilton Foliat, Hungerford, Berkshire., Sep. 19, 1942; VHP2006/31.IV.19
    - U.S. paratroopers of the 2nd Battalion, 503rd Parachute Infantry, marching to C-47 transport planes during maneuvers. Hungerford, Berkshire, England., Oct. 2, 1942; VHP2006/31.IV.20
    - Lieutenant Edmund J. Tomasik checks equipment of his planeload during maneuvers. Hungerford, Berkshire, England., Oct. 2, 1942; VHP2006/31.IV.21
    - Paratroopers inspecting main parachute and static line during maneuvers of the 2nd Battalion, 503rd Parachute Infantry., Oct. 2, 1942; VHP2006/31.IV.22
    - Lieutenant Fred Perry (of Dayton, Ohio), 2nd Battalion, 503rd Parachute Infantry, inspects engineer reserve parachutes of his men before going on maneuvers. Hungerford, Berkshire, England., Oct. 2, 1942; VHP2006/31.IV.23
    - Paratroopers of the 2nd Battalion, 503rd Parachute Infantry, embarking for training operation on a C-47 carrier plane. Hungerford, Berkshire, England., Oct. 2, 1942; VHP2006/31.IV.24
    - Paratroopers awaiting orders to jump during maneuvers. Hungerford, Berkshire, England., Oct. 2, 1942; VHP2006/31.IV.25
    - Paratrooper making a jump during overseas maneuvers. Hungerford, Berkshire, England., Oct. 2, 1942; VHP2006/31.IV.26
    - American paratroopers drawing rations for 40 hours before going on a training flight. Hungerford, England., Oct. 2, 1942; VHP2006/31.IV.27
    - 2nd Battalion, 509th Parachute Infantry. Maison Carree, Algeria., December 1942; VHP2006/31.IV.28
    - Lt. Col. Doyle R. Yardley, 2nd Bn., 509th Parachute Infantry, and John “Beaver” Thompson of the Chicago Tribune. Maison Carree, North Africa, 1942; VHP2006/31.IV.29
    - Brig. Gen. Lyman Lemnitzer decorating Captain Moir. Maison Carree, Algeria, North Africa., 1942; VHP2006/31.IV.30
    - Parachute Scout Co., 2nd Battalion, 509th Parachute Infantry. Oujda, North Africa., 1942; VHP2006/31.IV.31
    - 2nd Battalion, 509th Parachute Infantry. Camp Kunkle, Less Angades Airfield, Oujda, French Morocco, North Africa., June 5, 1943; VHP2006/31.IV.32
    - Co. E, 509th Parachute Battalion. Commanded by Captain Erven E. Boettner. Oujda, North Africa., 1943; VHP2006/31.IV.33
    - U.S. Parachute troops ready for action. Great Britain., 1943; VHP2006/31.IV.34
    - Morton Katz - Italy., 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.35
    - Practice jump area. Paestum, Italy., 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.36
    - Captain S.F. Newdigate, Commander of the Winchester Caatle, Lt. Col. William P. Yarborough, Commanding Officer of the 509th Parachute Infantry Battalion, Lt. Col. Roy A. Murray, Commanding Officer of the 4th Ranger Battalion; Aboard the Winchester Castle studying a model of the beach where troops aboard the ship will make their Assault. Mediterranean Sea., Jan. 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.37
    - Supplies are being loaded into adapted P-40, auxiliary belly gas tank for advanced troops behind enemy lines. Naples, Italy., Jan. 13, 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.38
    - K-rations being wrapped by Tech. Sgt. Lester C. McLaney (of Hartford, AL). Naples, Italy., Jan. 13, 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.39
    - Blanketed rations, rolled in salvage canvas, being tied securely with wire. Naples, Italy., Jan. 13, 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.40
    - A-5 containers loaded with supplies are being put aboard a C-47. 509th Parachute Infantry Station., Jan. 13, 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.41
    - Packing medical supplies at the 509th Parachute Infantry Battalion. Naples, Italy., Jan. 13, 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.42
    - Packing water. Naples, Italy., Jan. 13, 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.43
    - Packing mortar shells for dropping by parachute, 2-inch mortar shells are laid out, 12 on each side. Naples, Italy., Jan. 13, 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.44
    - Packing sheds at the 509th Parachute Infantry Battalion. Naples, Italy., Jan. 13, 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.45
    - Packing sheds at the 509th Parachute Infantry Battalion. Naples, Italy., Jan. 13, 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.46
    - Fleet of DUKWs in assault formation headed for the beach at Baia Bay, Pozzuoli Area, in rehearsal for Anzio attack by the 509th Parachute Infantry Battalion. Naples, Italy., Jan. 14, 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.47
    - 509th parachute Infantry Battalion. Practice operation supervised by Lt. Col. William P. Yarborough, Jr. (of Staunton, VA) landed from “DUKWS” at Baia Bay, Pozzuoli area, during rehearsal for attack on Anzio, Italy. Naples, Italy., Jan. 14, 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.48
    - Parachute infantry station: food, ammunition, medical supplies, gasoline, and water packed in containers, ready to be dropped by plane. Naples, Italy., Jan. 16, 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.49
    - "Circolo Nautica", a private club that was taken over and used as officers’ club. Naples, Italy., Spring 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.50
    - 93rd-95th Evacuation Hospital near Naples, Italy., 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.51
    - Lt. Talboy, Nurse at 33rd-95th Evacuation Hospital near Naples, Italy, 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.52
    - Anzio, Italy, March 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.53
    - Anzio Beachhead, Italy, March 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.54
    - Bombed building. Itri, Italy., March 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.55
    - Bombed building. Itri, Italy., Spring 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.56
    - Bombed building. Itri, Italy., Spring 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.57
    - Memorial Day. Formia, Italy., 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.58
    - Itri, Italy — Formia, Italy, May 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.59
    - Formia, Italy—Itri, Italy, 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.60
    - Morton N. Katz in Naples, Italy., Spring 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.61
    - Lt. Justin T. McCarthy. Piscinola, Italy., 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.62
    - USO Show. Piscinola District, Naples, Italy., Spring 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.63
    - USO Show. Piscinola District in Naples, Italy, Spring 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.64
    - “Clyde McCoy” - USO Show. Piscinola, Italy., Spring 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.65
    - Piscinola. Italy, Spring 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.66
    - A parade. Piscinola, Italy., Spring 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.67
    - Officers and men of the 509th Parachute Infantry Battalion. Naples, Italy., May 11, 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.68
      General note
      U.S. Army Photograph
    - Lt. Gen. Mark W. Clark, C.G. of Fifth Army, pins the Silver Star for Gallantry in action on Cpl. Roy W. David, 509th Parachute Infantry. Piscinola area, Italy., May 11, 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.69
    - Award ceremonies at U.S. Fifth Army Headquarters. Rome, Italy., June 8, 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.70
    - Morton N. Katz after his jump. Paestum, Italy, 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.71
    - Yacht trip - Italy., 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.72
    - South of Terracina, Italy., 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.73
    - Morton N. Katz in Southern France, 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.74
    - Presentation of awards. Southern France., 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.75
      Scope and Contents note
      Left to right: McCall, Campbell, Katz, Frederick, Tomasik, Pritchett, Oldham, Kelly
    - Men and equipment are dropped from C-47 transport aircraft near Le Motte, France, to the First Airborne Task Force on D-Day during the 7th army invasion of Southern France., August 15, 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.76
    - American troops of the 509th Parachute Infantry Battalion, 1st Airborne Task Force (who liberated southern France); During the opening operations of the Seventh Army Invasion., August 16, 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.77
    - Staff Sgt. Paul B. Huff, Company A, 509th Parachute Infantry Battalion, steps from a plane. He is the first paratrooper to receive the Medal of Honor. Miami Air Field, Miami, FL., August 21, 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.78
    - Staff Sgt. Paul B. Huff. Miami Air Field, Miami, FL., August 21, 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.79
    - Staff Sgt. Paul B. Huff pauses for a refreshment. Miami Air Field, Miami, FL., August 21, 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.80
    - Germans who died when the 509th Parachute Infantry Battalion of the 3rd Armored Division fought the 1st and 2nd Battalions of the 25th SS Panzer Grenadier Regiment, 12th SS Panzer Grensdier Division., December 29, 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.81
    - A paratrooper (right) thanks the French fighter who saved his life, Monsieur Mare Rainault. Center: Mademoiselle Nicola Celebonovitch, who secured a .45 (seen in her belt) and led the paratroopers to a group of hidden Germans. Rainault received the Silver Star for his work on D-Day. France, 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.82
    - Staff Sgt. Paul B. Huff. Picture taken soon after he won his wings at the Parachute School at Fort Benning, GA., 1944; VHP2006/31.IV.83
    - Paratroopers of Company A, 509th Parachute Infantry Battalion, 7th Armored Division (camouflaged in white), utilize a crude sled to bring a fellow soldier in for medical aid in the snow. Born, Belgium., January 21, 1945; VHP2006/31.IV.84
    - Paratroopers of the 509th Parachute Infantry Battalion prepare to leave Born, Belgium, to take a new objective at Hunnington. Born, Belgium., January 22, 1945; VHP2006/31.IV.85
    - Troops of the 509th Parachute Infantry Battalion, 7th Armored Division, move toward enemy positions beyond St. Vith, Belgium., January 24, 1945; VHP2006/31.IV.86
    - Rest Center (Morton Stayed at Hotel California Cannes, Southern France, August 1945; VHP2006/31.IV.87
    - Pool at Rest Center. Cannes, Southern France, August 1945; VHP2006/31.IV.88
    - Pool at Rest Center. Cannes, Southern France, August 1945; VHP2006/31.IV.89
    - Rest Center, view from the pool. Cannes, Southern France, August 1945; VHP2006/31.IV.90
    - A View from aboard the Queen Mary with Statue of Liberty in center background., 1945; VHP2006/31.IV.91
    - Morton N. Katz aboard Queen Mary on the way home., December 1945; VHP2006/31.IV.92
    - Colonel Kopesak, XIII Corps and Ft. Devens Commander, presents Lt. Col. Morton N. Katz, with Superior Unit Certificate., August 5th, 1963; VHP2006/31.IV.93
    - Lt. Col. Morton N. Katz is presented the Superior Unit Award by Col. Maurice D. Stratta, Deputy Commander XIII Corps., August 3rd, 1964; VHP2006/31.IV.94
    - Morton N. Katz, February 1968; VHP2006/31.IV.95
    - Back left-right: Col. Morton N. Katz, Governor Ella T. Grasso, Shirley D. Katz Front: Naomi P. Katz, Rachel A. Katz; Niantic, CT, June 9, 1979; VHP2006/31.IV.96
    - U.S. Army Airborne Division; 50th Anniversary; Washington, D.C., 1990; VHP2006/31.IV.97
    - Left - right: Dennis Irvin, Morton Katz, Ken Shaker; Veterans Day Parade. New York City., November 11, 1995; VHP2006/31.IV.98
    - Reunion of the 509th Parachute Infantry Battalion. Fayetteville, North Carolina., 2000; VHP2006/31.IV.99
    - Captain Charles C.H. Howland (from Tallapoosa, GA) of the 509th Parachute Infantry Battalion (born in Belgium, K.I.A. January 1945), VHP2006/31.IV.100
    - Morton N. Katz, 1940s; VHP2006/31.IV.101
    - Morton N. Katz, 1940s; VHP2006/31.IV.102
    - Reunion for the 509th Parachute Infantry Battalion, n.d.; VHP2006/31.IV.103
    - Parachute Test Platoon, n.d.; VHP2006/31.IV.104
      "All volunteers, but McLaney became chief rigger of the 509th Parachute Infantry Battalion. At Fort Benning, GA, on August 16, 1940, he orchestrated the U.S. Army’s 1st mass static line jump. As a result, August 16th is known as National Airborne Day. U.S. Army Photograph"
    - Morton Katz at the time of interview, November 2006; VHP2006/31.IV.105
  - Subseries B: Moving Images, VHP2006/31.IVb
    - Oral history interview with Morton N. Katz, November 15, 2006; VHP2006/31.IVb.1 (Disk DVD VHP2006/31, Box VHP Interview 2006)